<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>

<news xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

  <item>
    <year>2006</year>
    <month>01</month>
    <day>31</day>
    <title>
      <h:a href="http://nix.cs.uu.nl/dist/nix/nixpkgs-0.9/">Nixpkgs
      0.9</h:a> released
    </title>
    <description>
      Announcement is <a
      href="http://mail.cs.uu.nl/pipermail/nix-dev/2006-January/000121.html">here</a>.
    </description>      
  </item>

  <item>
    <year>2006</year>
    <month>01</month>
    <day>18</day>
    <title>
      PhD thesis defended
    </title>
    <description>
      Eelco Dolstra successfully defended his <a
      href="docs/papers.html#dolstra06thesis">PhD thesis</a> on the
      purely functional deployment model, a.k.a. Nix.
    </description>      
  </item>

  <item>
    <year>2005</year>
    <month>09</month>
    <day>21</day>
    <title>
      <h:a href="http://nix.cs.uu.nl/dist/nix/nix-0.9.2/">Nix
      0.9.2</h:a> released
    </title>
    <description>
      This is a bug fix release that addresses some problems on Mac OS
      X.
    </description>      
  </item>

  <item>
    <year>2005</year>
    <month>09</month>
    <day>16</day>
    <title>
      <h:a href="http://nix.cs.uu.nl/dist/nix/nix-0.9/">Nix 0.9</h:a>
      released
    </title>
    <description>
      This is a new major release that provides quite a few
      performance improvements and bug fixes, as well as a number of
      new features.  Read the <h:a
      href="http://nix.cs.uu.nl/dist/nix/nix-0.9/release-notes/">release
      notes</h:a> for details.
    </description>      
  </item>

  <item>
    <year>2005</year>
    <month>07</month>
    <day>28</day>
    <title>
      Secure sharing paper accepted for ASE 2005
    </title>
    <description>
      The paper “Secure Sharing Between Untrusted Users in a
      Transparent Source/Binary Deployment Model” has been accepted
      at <a href="http://www.ase-conference.org/">ASE 2005</a>.  This
      paper describes how a Nix store can be securely shared by
      multiple users who may not trust each other; i.e., how do we
      prevent one user from installing a Trojan horse that is
      subsequently executed by some other user?
    </description>      
  </item>

  <item>
    <year>2005</year>
    <month>07</month>
    <day>22</day>
    <title>
      Service deployment paper accepted for SCM-12
    </title>
    <description>
      The paper “Service Configuration Management” (accepted at the
      <h:a href="http://www.cs.ucsc.edu/~ejw/scm12/">12th
      International Workshop on Software Configuration
      Management</h:a>) describes how we can rather easily deploy
      “services” (e.g., complete webserver configurations such as our
      <h:a href="http://svn.cs.uu.nl">Subversion server</h:a>) through
      Nix by treating the non-component parts (such as configuration
      files, control scripts and static data) as components that are
      built by Nix expressions.  The result is that all advantages
      that Nix offers to software deployment also extend to service
      deployment, such as the ability to easily have multiple
      configuration side by side, to roll back configurations, and to
      identify the precise dependencies of a configuration.
    </description>      
  </item>

  <item>
    <year>2005</year>
    <month>02</month>
    <day>17</day>
    <title>
      Patching paper accepted for CBSE 2005
    </title>
    <description>
      The paper “Efficient Upgrading in a Purely Functional Component
      Deployment Model” has been accepted at <a
      href="http://www.sei.cmu.edu/pacc/CBSE2005/">CBSE 2005</a>.  It
      describes how we can deploy updates to Nix packages efficiently,
      even if “fundamental” packages like Glibc are updated (which
      cause a rebuild of all dependent packages), by deploying binary
      patches between components in the Nix store.  Includes
      techniques such as patch chaining and computing deltas between
      archive files.
    </description>      
  </item>

  <item>
    <year>2003</year>
    <month>12</month>
    <day>16</day>
    <title>
      Paper “Imposing a Memory Management Discipline on Software
      Deployment” accepted for presentation at ICSE 2004!
    </title>
    <description>
      The first Nix paper.
    </description>      
  </item>

</news>
